Register of the Tom Mboya papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Tom Mboya papers
1950-1969
2002C32
Hoover Institution Archives
73 manuscript boxes (29.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches, memoranda, reports, studies, minutes, and printed matter, relating to political, social and economic conditions in Kenya, trade unions and education in Kenya, Kenyan foreign relations, and pan-Africanism. Also available on microfilm (82 reels).
Mboya, Tom
Access
Microfilm use only. Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (83 reels).
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1930 Born, Kenya
1950s Works for Nairobi City Council as a sanitary inspector
1953 July Attends Third World Conference of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions in Stockholm
1953 October Becomes Secretary General of the Kenya Federation of Registered Trade Unions, subsequently the Kenya Federation of Labor
1955-1956 Studies at Oxford University
1956 Undertakes first speaking tour of the United States
1957 Elected Member of the Legislative Council of Kenya
1958 December Serves as chairman of the All African Peoples Conference in Accra, Ghana
1959 Visits the United States and forms the African-American Students Foundation in conjunction with William Scheinman. This foundation initiates the student airlift program that brings Kenyan students to the United States and Canada
1960 Becomes Secretary General of the Kenya African National Union (KANU), a political party which supports Jomo Kenyatta Supervises second student airlift program
1960 January-February Participates in the Lancaster House negotiations on Kenyan independence, in London
1962 Participates in second Lancaster House conference on Kenyan independence Becomes Minister for Labor
1963 Author, Freedom and After
1963-1964 Serves as Minister for Justice and Constitutional Affairs
1964-1969 Serves as Minister for Economic Planning and Development
1969 July 5 Assassinated in Nairobi
Scope and Content Note
Until his untimely death in 1969 at the hands of an assassin, Tom Mboya was a major figure in the political landscape of Kenya, being widely viewed as a likely successor to the first president of independent Kenya, Jomo Kenyatta. In a relatively short but extremely busy lifetime, Mboya assumed a variety of often overlapping roles: labor leader, nationalist militant, politician, Pan-Africanist, and educator. His many activities brought Mboya to prominence, both across Africa and internationally, and his numerous travels and speaking engagements further enhanced his image as rising star of African politics.
Acquired in 2001, the Tom Mboya collection in the Hoover Institution Archives provides a documentary record of this varied career, and as such represents a significant resource for scholarship on modern Africa. It is, of course, especially relevant to the study of Kenya, both before and after independence, but the collection also contains materials that illuminate aspects of Cold War politics in Africa, as well as extensive documentation on programs bringing Kenyan students to the United States for university study.
Mboya first achieved recognition as a trade unionist in a Kenya that was still a British colony, and his involvement with the Kenyan independence movement drew him into politics on a wider stage. He used his position as Secretary General of the Kenya Federation of Labor to press for the detained Kenyatta's release from British custody, and was instrumental in the formation of the Kenya African National Union (KANU), the main political party of the African population in the country, winning a seat in the Kenyan parliament as a KANU candidate. Mboya became Secretary General of KANU, and participated in the two rounds of negotiations with Britain that resulted in the achievement of Kenyan independence in 1963.
Mboya served in a number of ministerial posters under the presidency of Kenyatta, and was Minister for Economic Planning and Development in the years immediately prior to his death. While in government, Mboya retained his position as head of KANU, and was a firm opponent of tribalism as a factor in post-colonial Kenyan politics. It is believed that tribal rivalries, and their influence in the struggle to succeed Kenyatta, were a factor in Mboya's assassination, the full story of which has never been explicated. The Mboya collection itself does not provide any further answers to the questions surrounding Mboya's killing.
The unorthodox series and subseries headings in the Mboya register reflect the original arrangement and description of the materials as established by Tom Mboya and his heirs. The series order reflects the shipping manifest accompanying the collection. The original reference number for each subseries is provided in parenthesis after each subseries heading in the register, and discrepancies are noted when the contents of the subseries are at variance with the heading. There is no separate series for speeches and writings, but significant speeches and articles by Tom Mboya are listed in the register as they occur in the collection. There is a PUBLIC AFFAIRS series that contains a number of speeches and writings by Mboya.
Throughout his public career, Mboya conducted an extensive official correspondence, and in the collection this is grouped largely according to organization or government department. There are separate TRADE UNIONS and KANU series, as well as one for foreign correspondence (see GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE WITH FOREIGN COUNTRIES). Materials can be found in these series concerning Mboya's relations with the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, and his correspondence in these series with American officials such as Jay Lovestone and Irving Brown is of importance in understanding American policies toward Africa. The extensive MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE series at the end of the collection contains both official and personal correspondence, much of which is grouped by country. This series also contains materials concerning Mboya's official visit to Australia in 1964.
There is a large amount of materials in the collection that pertains to Kenyan domestic politics, some of which provide a glimpse into the role played by tribal divisions within the country. The PARLIAMENT and POLITICS series also record Mboya's many dealings with constituents as a Member of the Legislative Council, and in his ministerial posts.
In 1959, Tom Mboya initiated a significant effort to provide Kenyan students with opportunities to attend universities abroad, especially in the United States and Canada, and there is a great deal of material concerning the student airlift program associated with his name (see especially the INSTITUTES AND BURSARIES and the UNIVERSITIES series in the collection).
Additional materials concerning the airlift and about Mboya himself can be found in the William X. Scheinman collection in the Hoover Institution Archives. The Scheinman collection contains drafts and proofs of Mboya's autobiography, Freedom and After, and a number of speeches and articles by him. There are also audiovisual materials concerning Mboya in the Scheinman collection.
Africa.; Education--Kenya.; Education.; Kenya--Economic conditions.; Kenya--Foreign relations.; Kenya--Politics and government.; Kenya--Social conditions.; Kenya.; Labor movement--Kenya.; Pan-Africanism.; Statesmen--Kenya.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Other Finding Aids note
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- Societies and Associations Series, 1953-1969
  Scope and Contents note
  Accounts, agenda, bulletins, circulars, clippings, correspondence, flier, lease, legislative proposals, minutes of meetings, memoranda, newsletters, notices, press release, receipts, reports, resolution, rules and regulations, speeches, largely relating to Tom Mboya's tenure as Kenyan Minister of Economic Planning and Development, Minister of Labor, and Member of the City Council of Nairobi, arranged by subject or organization in numerical sequence according to original file numbers
  Correspondence and other materials, arranged by subject or organization, and pertaining mainly to Tom Mboya's activities as Kenyan Minister of Economic Planning and Development, Minister of Labor, and Member of the City Council of Nairobi
  - Chambers of Commerce and Industry (original reference indication, SA/1). Circulars, correspondence, and minutes of meetings, largely relating to the Kenya National Chamber of Commerce and Industry and the Nairobi Chamber of Commerce, 1965-1969 (Reel 1)
    Box/Folder 1: 1
  - Kenya Institute of Management (SA/2). Correspondence, minutes of meetings, notices, and reports, 1966-1969
    Box/Folder 1: 2
  - East African Management Foundation (SA/3). Correspondence, minutes of meetings, and notices, 1966-1969
    Box/Folder 1: 3
  - Kenya Red Cross Society (SA/4). Correspondence, newsletters, and reports, 1966-1968
    Box/Folder 1: 4
  - Kenya National Union of Teachers (SA/5). Correspondence and reports, 1969
    Box/Folder 1: 5
  - Religious subjects (SA/6). Correspondence, legislative proposals, and reports, primarily concerning religious organizations in Kenya
    - 1966-1967
      Box/Folder 1: 6
    - 1968-1969
      Box/Folder 1: 7
  - Kenya Girl Guides Association (SA/7). Correspondence and reports, 1967-1968
    Box/Folder 1: 8
  - Freedom from Hunger Campaign (SA/8). Bulletins, correspondence, receipts, and reports
    - 1965 (Reel 2)
      Box/Folder 1: 9
    - 1966-1968
      Box/Folder 1: 10
  - Nairobi Motor Club (SA/9). Accounts, agenda, notices, and minutes of meetings, 1968-1969
    Box/Folder 2: 1
  - American Committee on Africa (SA/10). Clipping, correspondence, flier, reports, and speech, 1959-1966
    Box/Folder 2: 2. Includes letters exchanged between Tom Mboya and George M. Houser
  - World Assembly of Youth (SA/11). Circular, correspondence, minutes of meeting, speech, 1960-1963
    Box/Folder 2: 3
  - African Health Inspectors Association (SA/12). Circulars, correspondence, and reports, 1953-1954
    Box/Folder 2: 4
  - Clubs and Societies - General (SA/13). Bulletins, circulars, correspondence, minutes of meetings, and reports, relating to voluntary organizations in Kenya
    - 1966-1967
      Box/Folder 2: 5
    - 1968
      Box/Folder 2: 6
  - Abulayia Association of East Africa (SA/14). Correspondence and resolution, 1968
    Box/Folder 2: 7
  - Young Men's and Women's Christian Associations (SA/15). Correspondence, 1968
    Box/Folder 2: 8
  - Youth Council of Kenya (SA/16). Correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports, and speeches
    - 1958-1965 (Reel 3)
      Box/Folder 2: 9. Includes typescripts of two speeches by Tom Mboya, 1964 September 22 and November 24, and correspondence with Miriam Makeba
    - 1966-1969
      Box/Folder 2: 10
  - Chartered Institute of Secretaries (SA/17). Correspondence and speech, 1962-1964
    Box/Folder 2: 11. Includes typescript of a speech made by Tom Mboya, 1964 March 13
  - Meetings of Luo Leaders (SA/18). Clippings, correspondence, minutes of meetings, reports, and speeches
    - 1967
      Box/Folder 3: 1-2
    - 1968-1969
      Box/Folder 3: 3
  - African Muslim Association (SA/19). Clippings, correspondence, minutes of meetings, press release, and reports, 1957-1965 (Reel 4)
    Box/Folder 3: 4
  - Luo Union Football Club (SA/20). Correspondence, notice, reports, and rules and regulations, 1964-1968
    Box/Folder 3: 5
  - Youth - General (SA/21). Correspondence, minutes of meetings, and reports, 1962-1968
    Box/Folder 3: 6. Includes materials relating to the Kenya Girl Guides Association, the Kenya Youth Hostels Association, and the Nairobi City Boy Scouts Association
  - Christian Council of Kenya and Religious Matters (SA/22). Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and speech, 1962-1968
    Box/Folder 4: 1. Includes typescript of a speech by Tom Mboya, 1967 June 30, and some letters addressed to or written by Pamela Mboya
  - National Council of Women of Kenya (SA/23). Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, 1966-1968
    Box/Folder 4: 2
  - Staff Welfare Associations (SA/24). Correspondence and reports, 1967-1969
    Box/Folder 4: 3. Includes materials relating to the Salvation Army in Kenya
  - Child Welfare Society of Kenya (SA/25). Correspondence and reports, 1963-1969
    Box/Folder 4: 4
  - Lumumba Institute and Trust (SA/26). Correspondence, lease, and reports, 1965-1967 (Reel 5)
    Box/Folder 4: 5
- KANU (Kenya African National Union) Series, 1956-1968
  Accounts, biography, clippings, constitution, constitutional amendments and proposals, correspondence, lists, manifestos, memoranda, minutes of meetings, organizational chart, press releases, program, receipts, reports, speeches, statement, transcript, largely relating to Tom Mboya's activities as Secretary-General sequence according to original file numbers of KANU, arranged by physical form or subject in numerical sequence according to original file numbers
  Correspondence and other materials, arranged by form or subject, and pertaining mainly to Tom Mboya's activities as Secretary General of the Kenya African National Union (KANU)
  - KANU Constitution (original reference number, K/1). Constitutional proposals and amendments, memoranda, organizational chart, and statement, 1966
    Box/Folder 4: 6
  - Election Manifestos (K/1/1). Correspondence and manifestos, 1957-1966
    Box/Folder 4: 7. Includes statement on election policy by Tom Mboya, 1957
  - KANU Parliamentary Group (K/2). Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, press releases, reports, and transcript
    - 1957-1960
      Box/Folder 4: 8. Includes transcript of remarks made by Tom Mboya, 1960 December 12
    - 1961
      Box/Folder 4: 9
  - KANU Press Releases (K/3). Biography, clippings, correspondence, and press releases, including many containing statements by Tom Mboya
    - 1956-1960
      Box/Folder 5: 1. Includes typescript chapter, with a biography of Tom Mboya, from a book by Thomas Patrick Melady, 1960
    - 1961
      Box/Folder 5: 2
  - Republic Celebrations (K/4). Correspondence, invitation, memoranda, minutes of meetings, press releases, photographs, and speech, 1964-1968
    Box/Folder 5: 3. Includes typescript of a speech by Tom Mboya, 1968 December 12
  - Independence Celebrations (K/5). Working program for visit to Kenya by British royal party, 1963
    Box/Folder 5: 4
  - List of Invited Guests - 1962 (K/6). Lists of guests invited to the wedding of Tom and Pamela Mboya, and accompanying correspondence (Reel 6)
    Box/Folder 5: 5
  - KANU Candidates in Elections (ML/POL/1(6). Correspondence and candidate lists, 1963
    Box/Folder 5: 6
  - Applications for Special Seats (K/7). Correspondence and campaign flyer, 1963
    Box/Folder 5: 7
  - KANU Kamukunji Sub-branch (K/8). Correspondence and reports, 1968
    Box/Folder 5: 8
  - General Correspondence. Accounts, clippings, correspondence, press releases, receipts, speech, and reports
    - Volume one, (K/9/v.1), 1962
      - Nos. 1-150 (first series)
        Box/Folder 5: 9. Includes typescript (no. 42) of a speech by Jomo Kenyatta
      - Nos. 51-199 (second series)
        Box/Folder 6: 1
      - Nos. 200-274
        Box/Folder 6: 2
    - Volume two, (K/9/v.2), 1960-1965 (Reel 7)
      Box/Folder 6: 3
    - Volume three (K/9/v.3)
      - 1960
        Box/Folder 6: 4
      - 1961
        Box/Folder 6: 5
    - Volume four, (K/9/v.4), 1963-1964
      Box/Folder 6: 6
    - Volume five, (K/9/v.5), 1966
      Box/Folder 7: 1
    - Volume six (K/9/v.6)
      - 1964 (Reel 8)
        Box/Folder 7: 2
      - 1965
        Box/Folder 7: 3
      - 1966
        Box/Folder 7: 4
    - Volume seven, (K/9/v.7), 1963-1964
      - Nos. 1-100
        Box/Folder 7: 5
      - Nos. 101-200
        Box/Folder 7: 6
      - Nos. 201-325
        Box/Folder 8: 1
    - Volume eight, (K/9/v.8), 1963
      - Nos. 1-100 (Reel 9)
        Box/Folder 8: 2
      - Nos. 101-245
        Box/Folder 8: 3
    - Volume nine, (K/9/v.9), 1963-1964
      - Nos. 1-100
        Box/Folder 8: 4
      - Nos. 101-221
        Box/Folder 8: 5
    - Volume ten (K/9/v.10)
      - 1963-1964
        Box/Folder 8: 6
      - 1965-1966
        Box/Folder 8: 7
    - Volume eleven, (K/9/v.11), 1963
      - Nos. 1-100 (Reel 10)
        Box/Folder 9: 1
      - Nos. 101-213
        Box/Folder 9: 2
    - Volume twelve, (K/9/v.12), 1963
      - Nos. 1-100
        Box/Folder 9: 3
      - Nos. 101-200
        Box/Folder 9: 4
      - Nos. 201-300
        Box/Folder 9: 5
      - Nos. 301-390
        Box/Folder 9: 6
    - Volume thirteen, (K/9/v.13), 1961
      - January-June (Reel 11)
        Box/Folder 9: 7
      - July-October
        Box/Folder 10: 1
    - Volume fourteen, (K/9/v.14), 1962-1963
      - Nos. 1-100
        Box/Folder 10: 2
      - Nos. 101-200
        Box/Folder 10: 3
      - Nos. 201-340
        Box/Folder 10: 4
    - Volume fifteen, (K/9/v.15), 1967
      Box/Folder 10: 5
    - Volume sixteen, (K/9/v.16), 1968 (Reel 12)
      Box/Folder 10: 6
  - Kenya People's Union (P/1). Constitution, correspondence, memoranda, and press release, 1966
    Box/Folder 11: 1
  - People's Convention Party (P/2). Constitution and correspondence, 1959-1960
    Box/Folder 11: 2
  - General Correspondence on Political Matters. Clippings, correspondence, and reports
    - Volume one, (P/3/v.1), 1962-1963
      - Nos. 1-100
        Box/Folder 11: 3
      - Nos. 101-157
        Box/Folder 11: 4
    - Volume two, (P/3/v.2), 1959-1967 (Reel 13)
      Box/Folder 11: 5
- Politics Series, 1956-1966
  Bulletins, clippings, correspondence, minutes of meetings, press releases, programs, serial issues, speech, and reports, largely relating to Tom Mboya's activities as Minister of Labor and as Secretary-General of KANU, arranged by subject or organization in numerical sequence according to original file numbers
  - Kenya We Want Convention (P/4). Correspondence, minutes of meetings, programs, speech, and reports, 1962-1963
    Box/Folder 11: 6. Includes typescript of a speech by Tom Mboya, undated
  - Political Organizations (P/5). Correspondence, press releases, and reports, 1960-1963
    Box/Folder 12: 1
  - Correspondence with Political Parties Abroad. Bulletins, correspondence, and reports
    - Volume one, (P/6/v.1), 1965-1966
      Box/Folder 12: 2
    - Volume two, (P/6/v.2), 1961-1963
      Box/Folder 12: 3
  - Correspondence with Colonial Office (P/8). Clipping, correspondence, press releases, and reports, 1956-1962
    Box/Folder 12: 4. Includes letters exchanged between Tom Mboya and Austen Albu, Fenner Brockway, James Callaghan, James Johnson, John Stonehouse, and Anthony Wedgwood Benn
  - Pan-African Movements (P/8/1). Clippings, correspondence, press releases, serial issues, speeches, and reports, 1963-1964
    Box/Folder 12: 5. Includes printed copies of two articles by Tom Mboya, with foreign translations of one of them
- Parliament Series, 1960-1969
  Agendas, articles, bills, briefing papers, bulletins, clippings, correspondence, legislative proposals, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, notices, reports, speeches, transcripts, largely relating to Tom Mboya's activities as Kenyan Minister of Economic Planning and Development, Minister for Justice and Constitutional Affairs, and Member of the Legislative Council, arranged by subject, form, or organization in numerical sequence according to original file numbers. Includes documents concerning the 1962 Lancaster House negotiations on Kenyan independence
  Correspondence and other materials, listed by governmental body, subject, or form, and pertaining mainly to Tom Mboya's activities in Kenya as Member of the Legislative Council, Member of Parliament, Minister for Justice and Constitutional Affairs, and Minister of Economic Planning and Development. Additional documents relate to the 1962 Lancaster House negotiations on Kenyan independence, in which Tom Mboya participated as the representative of the Kenya African National Union (KANU)
  - Parliamentary Constituencies (LC/1). Correspondence and legal notices, 1966
    Box/Folder 12: 6
  - Parliament - General. Bulletins, correspondence, legal notices, minutes of meetings, receipts, transcripts of proceedings, and reports
    - Volume one (LC/2/v.1)
      - 1964-1967 (Reel 14)
        Box/Folder 12: 7
      - 1968
        Box/Folder 12: 8
    - Volume two, (LC/2/v.2), 1964-1969
      Box/Folder 13: 1
    - Volume three (LC/2/v.3)
      - 1962-1964
        Box/Folder 13: 2. Includes transcripts of remarks made by Tom Mboya
      - 1965-1967
        Box/Folder 13: 3
  - Economic Committee (LC/3). Correspondence and reports, 1966-1968
    Box/Folder 13: 4
  - Parliamentary Proceedings and Votes. Correspondence, legislative proposals, minutes of meetings, reports, and transcripts of proceedings
    - Volume one, (LC/4/v.1), 1969
      Box/Folder 13: 5
    - Volume two, (LC/4/v.2), 1963-1964 (Reel 15)
      Box/Folder 13: 6
    - Volume three, (LC/4/v.3)., 1963-1967
      Box/Folder 14: 1. Includes transcripts of remarks by Tom Mboya
    - Volume four, (LC/4/v.4), 1960-1961
      Box/Folder 14: 2
  - Bills and Motions (LC/5). Bills, correspondence, motions, and transcripts of proceedings, 1964-1966
    Box/Folder 14: 3
  - Notices of Motions (LC/6). Correspondence, memoranda, notices, and statements, 1965-1969
    Box/Folder 14: 4
  - Speaker's Committee (LC/7). Correspondence and minutes of meetings, 1965-1968 (Reel 16)
    Box/Folder 14: 5
  - Sessional Committee. Agendas, correspondence, and minutes of meetings
    - Volume one, (LC/8/v.1), 1965-1966
      Box/Folder 14: 6
    - Volume two, (LC/8/v.2), 1961-1966
      Box/Folder 14: 7
    - Volume three, (LC/8/v.3), 1960-1961
      Box/Folder 15: 1
  - Parliamentary Debates (LC/9). Correspondence, clippings, reports, statements, and transcripts of proceedings, including remarks by Tom Mboya
    - 1961 March-June (Reel 17)
      Box/Folder 15: 2
    - 1961 July-October
      Box/Folder 15: 3
  - Backbenchers Meetings (LC/10). Correspondence and minutes of meetings, 1964-1965
    Box/Folder 15: 4
  - Lancaster House Conference, 1962
    Agendas, article, bills, constitutional memoranda, correspondence, reports, and statements, 1960-1968
    - Volume one, (LC/11/v.1), 1960-1962
      Box/Folder 15: 5
    - Volume two, (LC/11/v.2)., 1962-1968
      Box/Folder 15: 6. Includes printed copy of an article by Tom Mboya, "East African Common Market: How We Did It," Ceres, 1968 November-December
  - Local Government - Constitutional Provisions (LG/1). Constitutional proposals, reports, and speech, 1963 (Reel 18)
    Box/Folder 16: 1. Includes typescript of a speech by Jomo Kenyatta, 1963 February
  - Land Policy - Squatters (LP/1). Briefing papers, memoranda, notes, and reports, 1966
    Box/Folder 16: 2
  - Correspondence with Nairobi City Treasurer (LG/2). Correspondence, press release, and reports, 1963
    Box/Folder 16: 3
  - South Nyanza County Council (LG/3). Minutes of meetings, 1967
    Box/Folder 16: 4
- Trade Unions Series, 1950-1968
  Agendas, application forms, article, bulletins, circular, clippings, constitutions, correspondence, invitation, lists, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, notices, press releases, receipts, regulations, reports, resolution, rules, serial issues, speeches, statements, and transcript, largely relating to Tom Mboya's activities as Secretary General of the Kenya Federation of Labor (KFL) and as Kenyan Minister for Labor, arranged by organization or subject in numerical sequence according to original file numbers